Daf is דף Daf מ"ט, Mem-tet, 49, and we're actually a rough
ahead, we're a little bit into the דף, daf, and the issue
here has been the following, just that the משנה mishna spoke about
not benefiting from an אשרה Asherah tree, a tree that was worshipped
as עבודה זרה, Avodah Zarah, we'll go with that for now. And
one of the issues is planting underneath it in the
winter where you're not benefiting from the shade, but you might benefit
from the fact that the droppings off of the trees will serve
as fertilizer. So that was Rabbi Yosef said that that was a
problem, the חכמים Chakhamim did not, we're trying to get to the
bottom of what that debate is about. So one way of understanding
it is the debate about זה וזה גורם. Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem. If
you have two things that contribute to something, the effect of something,
multiple things contribute to a plant's growth: sunlight, water, nutrients, so that
would not be זה וזה גורם. Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem. תוספות Tosafot makes
it clear that זה וזה גורם Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem is that they're
doing contributing equally to one particular way of causing the plant to
grow. So you have both the nutrients from the ground and the
nutrients from the tree, and is that going to be considered like
you got benefit from the עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah because it wasn't
all coming from the tree. Now of course, one possible thing to
be asking, which the גמרא Gemara actually is going to get into
today, is like, well, did you need the tree? Were they both
necessary? Was one of them dominant? etc., etc. So we'll touch on
some of that today. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara thinks that that's the
debate of Rabbi Yosef and the חכמים, Chakhamim, but it's got a
problem because based on another discussion about grinding up an idol and
scattering it where Rabbi Yosef was not worried that that would contribute
to some plant's growth and the חכמים Chakhamim were, it sounded like
they held the opposite position. So right now, the גמרא's Gemara claim
is that everybody holds זה וזה גורם Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem is a
problem, and the reason that the חכמים Chakhamim are not bothered in
our משנה mishna is because the benefit of the fertilizing that you
get from the tree
is counterbalanced, it's offset by the detriment of the tree providing shade.
So you look at it sort of in the macro and not
in the micro. Okay, but that in principle, everybody holds זה וזה
גורם Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem is a problem. The problem that the גמרא
Gemara had when we ended up yesterday was that it seemed like
actually from another source that Rabbi Yosef held that זה וזה גורם
Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem again was not a problem. So let's maybe re-read
that, okay? So, I guess we'll since we were ahead but now
we'll go back and just re-read it so we get the we
build up the momentum. Three lines from the bottom on מ"ח mem-chet
עמוד ב'. amud bet. והתנן, Ve-hatnan,
okay, וסבר ve-savar Rabbi Yosef זה וזה גורם אסור? Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem
asur? Do you really think that Rabbi Yosef really everybody holds זה
וזה גורם Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem is forbidden? והתנן, Ve-hatnan, three lines from
the bottom on מ"ח mem-chet עמוד ב', amud bet, רבי יוסי אומר,
Rabbi Yosei omer, נוטעין ייחוסו של ערלה ואין נוטעין אגוזו של ערלה.
notin ikhusho shel orlah ve-ein notin eglo shel orlah.
You can plant a sapling of an ערלה orlah tree because that's
not forbidden in הנאה, hana'ah, only the fruit is, but you can't
plant a nut of an ערלה orlah tree, which is forbidden in
הנאה, hana'ah, מפני שהוא פרי mipnei she-hu peri because it's a fruit.
אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda amar Rav, מודה רבי
יוסי שאם נטע והבריך והרכיב מותר. modeh Rabbi Yosei she-im nata ve-hivrkh
ve-hirkiv mutar. That's considered benefit, but בדיעבד bedi'avad if you did it
and you planted the nut and you, you know, and you grafted
a branch or whatever, the resulting fruit would be actually permissible. Why?
Because even though you now have like gotten benefit, but since in
the end the resulting fruit was זה וזה גורם Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem
so again, תוספות Tosafot wants to focus not on the planting of
the nut because that doesn't fit his theory, so he basically says
let's say you graft a branch. So you graft a branch, the
branch that you started with and the tree that it was grafted
onto, both directly sort of contribute to the growth of the fruit,
that's a זה וזה גורם. Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem. ותניא נמי הכי Ve-tanya
nami hakhi מותר. mutar. מודה רבי יוסי שאם נטע והבריך והרכיב מותר.
modeh Rabbi Yosei she-im nata ve-hivrkh ve-hirkiv mutar. Rabbi Yosef said that
if you did those things, it's permissible. So you see Rabbi Yosef
sounds like זה וזה גורם Zeh ve-Zeh Gorem is permissible, okay, and
that doesn't fit with our current theory that everybody holds it's forbidden.
וכי תימא שאני ליה לרבי יוסי בין שאר איסורין לעבודה כוכבים? Ve-khi
tema shani leh le-Rabbi Yosei bein she'ar issurin le-avodah kokhavim? Maybe Rabbi
Yosef would say by other things it's permissible, by עבודה זרה Avodah
Zarah I'm strict and I consider that to be a problem. ומי
שאני ליה? U-mi shani leh? But does he really make a difference?
והתניא Ve-hatanya we taught in the ברייתא, baraita, שדה שנזדבלה בזבל עבודה
כוכבים. sadeh she-nizdabla be-zevel avodah kokhavim.
You basically fertilized the field with dung of עבודה כוכבים. Avodah Kokhavim.
So you have to imagine what's the case of dung of עבודה
כוכבים? Avodah Kokhavim? Is it produced by a cow that was worshipped
as עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? Is it an actual some type of
an idol that's worshipped by bringing עבודה זרה? Avodah Zarah? Exactly. Anyway,
we're not going to worry about those specifics right now. וכן פרה
שנספטמה בכשיני עבודה כוכבים, Ve-khen parah she-nispitma be-khashinei avodah kokhavim, or a
cow that was fattened with, what do you call it, with grain
like, you know, with some type of a wheat type of a
thing, or how do they say כשינין? kashinin? How does he translate
כשינין? kashinin? Whatever it is. Okay, anyway, some type of a, you
know, some type of a fodder of עבודה זרה. Avodah Zarah. תניא
חדא, Tanya khada,
so now this field and this cow have been improved by these
things, but they're also improved by the other stuff that they eat
and the other fertilizer. So in that case, תניא חדא tanya khada
one ברייתא baraita teaches שדה תיזרע פרה תישחט, sadeh tizzara parah tishakhet,
that you have that you can go ahead, okay, you shouldn't have
done it, but now that
you vetch, oh that helps a lot. Okay, that now what? בדיעבד?
bedieved? Whatever, anyway, what? Anyway, so one ברייתא baraita says that it's
okay because even so you did
it, now you did it, it's you shouldn't have done it, but
now stuff that will grow will be a זה וזה גורם Zeh
ve-Zeh Gorem and it won't be a problem. ותניא אידך, Ve-tanya idakh,
another ברייתא baraita says... And the cow gets skinny, so you know,
so it could be seen as counteracting the benefit that you got
from feeding it. All right, anyway, so we, so the bottom line
is, it seems like this is a debate about זה וזה גורם
zeh v'zeh gorem, *zeh v'zeh gorem*, right? That these things are being
fed by multiple sources, and is that a problem? You're not supposed
to do that, but if you did that, does that create a
problem? So here we have a debate by עבודה זרה avodah zarah.
*avodah zarah* whether זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem*
is a problem. And the only person we have until now that
has said, that we can hang our hat on, or that we
think we can hang our hat on, that says זה וזה גורם
zeh v'zeh gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem* is not a problem, is Rabbi
Yose, because of that ruling by ערלה *orlah* and the other ruling
by like grinding up the idol. So מאי לאו *mai lav*, says
the Gemara, the best way to explain this, these, this contradiction or
these two opinions is הא רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, והא רבנן Rabbanan
*ha Rabbi Yose veha Rabbanan*, that Rabbi Yose is of the opinion
זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem* is not an
issue. That would explain why he says you can grind up the
idol and scatter it to the wind, that would explain why he
says that if you benefit, that if you grafted the ערלה *orlah*
thing, that it's okay. That would explain why he would say that,
and that then he could be the author of this case, that
if you fed the cow with this vetch of עבודה זרה avodah
zarah. *avodah zarah*, that it's not a problem after the fact. Okay,
so this, if you put those things together, you can come up
with a theory that Rabbi Yose holds זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem* is not a problem. You'd have to explain
Rabbi Yose in our Mishnah, but at least that would explain all
of that evidence. So the Gemara says, לא Lo, *lo*, no, I
don't want to say that, I still want to say that Rabbi
Yose and the Rabbis both agree זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
*zeh v'zeh gorem* is a problem like we've been saying until now.
And maybe the Rabbi Yose by ערלה *orlah*, okay, maybe by עבודה
זרה avodah zarah *avodah zarah* at least everybody says זה וזה גורם
zeh v'zeh gorem... *zeh v'zeh gorem* is a problem, and maybe by
ערלה *orlah* Rabbi Yose is lenient. Okay, so now who is this
person in this case of the ברייתא baraita *braisa* we just brought,
that's a case of עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *avodah zarah*, that's going
to say זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem* is
okay. Who's going to be that person? So the Gemara says, you
know what, that's a debate not of Rabbi Yose and the Rabbis,
but הא רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer והא רבנן Rabbanan *ha Rabbi Eliezer
veha Rabbanan*, of Rabbi Eliezer and the Rabbis. הא רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer. והא רבנן rabbanan *ha Rabbi Eliezer veha Rabbanan*. Okay, it sounds
like you have in mind some debate of Rabbi Eliezer and the
Rabbis, that debate in זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem. *zeh v'zeh
gorem* by עבודה זרה Avodah Zarah *avodah zarah*. Okay, you want to
say Rabbi Yose and the Rabbis all agree it's a problem, this
is some debate of Rabbi Eliezer and the Rabbis. Which Rabbi Eliezer
and the Rabbis? Sounds like a rock team.
אילימא רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer
ורבנן דשאור *Eilayma Rabbi Eliezer veRabbanan de'se'or*. How about the case about
yeast? Okay, not yeast, I always say yeast because, you know, it
just shows my modern taste. I've actually been doing some recent reading
and listening, פסח *Pesach* is coming up, about sourdough. So we're, you
know, yeast is like a very modern invention that you get this
dry yeast or whatever. You know, actually sourdough is always the way
about how you make bread, you know, which is, you know, fermented
dough or whatever, but anyway, and then it sort of makes other
doughs into bread. Anyway, so the issue about sourdough, very relevant for
פסח *Pesach*. By the way, זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem *zeh
v'zeh gorem* is also relevant for פסח *Pesach* in other ways. You
have the whole issue about people that are מקפיד *makpid*, it's pretty
standard these days I think to be מקפיד *makpid*, I don't know,
you tell me what you do, buy your milk and buy your
eggs before פסח *Pesach* begins. You know about that? Because there's whole
questions about
if the cows or the chickens are eating the grain on פסח
*Pesach* and then they're making out of that the milk, I mean
I don't know, that's a pretty fast turnover that they should be
eating it on פסח *Pesach* and it comes to market already by
that time, I don't know what the turnover is, to me that
seems a little bit unlikely. But anyway, so it's a whole problem
of like a זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem*
and are you concerned about that for פסח *Pesach*. Anyway, so here's
a case where maybe we have a debate about this.
Now this is again Wait, you're saying the reason to buy the
milk is because they would have eaten because you're getting הנאה hana'ah
*hana'ah* from like חמץ *chametz*? Yeah. I thought it was because like,
the way I was always taught, like you know, maybe some like
grains or whatever like got in there and so on.
Maybe that too. I don't know, maybe that too. Okay, דתנן d'tan:
שאור של חולין chullin ושל תרומה terumah, *de'tnan se'or shel chulin veshel
terumah*, I mean that would make a little more sense, but either,
anyway, maybe because then it's בטל batel. *batel* if it's ערב פסח
*erev Pesach* and it's not בטל batel, *batel* on פסח *Pesach*. Anyway,
דתנן D'tan: שאור של חולין ושל תרומה terumah, *de'tnan se'or shel chulin
veshel terumah*. Now the funny thing is, is that we've already conceded
that Rabbi Eliezer, that Rabbi Yose holds זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem. *zeh v'zeh gorem* is okay by non-עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avodah
zarah*. So presumably we're looking for somebody who says it's okay by
עבודה זרה avoda zara. *avodah zarah*, but we're not turning to an
עבודה זרה avoda zara *avodah zarah* case. So anyway, we won't worry
about that right now. Okay, here's the debate. You have sourdough of
of normal bread and sourdough of תרומה terumah *terumah*. And you need
and in order to turn your dough and to get it to
ferment, you need a certain minimum amount of sourdough. And you now
that minimum amount is is coming half from the תרומה terumah *terumah*
and half from the חולין *chulin*. Okay, so it's a case of
זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem*, and here at
least we're being clear it's a זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
*zeh v'zeh gorem* and you need both, both are necessary. שאור של
חולין ושל תרומה terumah שנפלו לתוך עיסה *se'or shel chulin veshel terumah
she'naflu le'toch issah*, and they fell into the dough. לא lo, בזה
כדי להחמיץ ולא בזה כדי להחמיץ *lo be'zeh kedei le'hachmitz velo be'zeh
kedei le'hachmitz*. Each sourdough alone could not have done the job, so
that's helpful in understanding the parameters of זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem, *zeh v'zeh gorem*. Okay, ונתצרפו וחימצו, but they they worked together,
they understand the value of cooperation and therefore they together they made
the bread, they fermented the bread. Okay, רבי אליעזר אומר אחר האחרונה
אני בא. Rabbi Eliezer omer achar ha'achrona ani ba. If they fell
sequentially, you look at which one finished it. If the because then
you know, what's past is past. So the bread that fell the
first, the sourdough that fell first, fine, that's all past history. That
was בטל. batel. That didn't cause because the principle is, is that
if something causes fermentation, because it has such a powerful effect on
the object it's mixed to, it doesn't become בטל, batel. even if
it's only a trivial amount. Right? Normally if it's something is less
than a sixtieth, sometimes even smaller whatever, anyway, it gets nullified. But
if it causes fermentation, right, then it had a real powerful effect,
it's not בטל. batel. So what רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says makes
a lot of sense. He says look, the first one fell in,
it didn't cause fermentation. That became בטל. batel Now you have some
now the second one falls in. Ah, that now was the מכה
בפטיש makeh b'patish as we would say, that was the final blow,
that caused the fermentation. So the last one is the one that's
not בטל.
batel He's saying after the first the last one follows.
I understand, but that was past history. By the time the last
one fell in, the first one was already בטל batel and the
last one did the job.
Just like יציאת מצרים, Yetzias Mitzrayim, we remember that all the time.
What? You said past history, meaning like...
Alright, fine, Michael. Anyway, so that's רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer? רבי אליעזר
Rabbi Eliezer says you look at the last one, that makes a
lot of sense. וחכמים אומרים, v'Chachamim omrim, and the וחכמים Chachamim say,
בין שנפל איסור לכתחילה בין שנפל איסור לבסוף אינו אסור עד שיהא
בו כדי להחמיץ. bein shenafal issur l'chatchilah bein shenafal issur l'vasof eino
assur ad sheyehei bo k'dei l'hachmitz. But the וחכמים Chachamim say even
if the איסור issur fell in at the end, so you could
try to pin it all on the איסור, issur, on the תרומה,
terumah they say it doesn't matter. You take a step back, okay,
this Michael likes this one, you take a step back and you
say, wait a minute, wait, let's let's understand what actually is happening
here and you appreciate the fact that both of them are jointly
causing it. It's not just being called caused by the איסור. issur.
And therefore the וחכמים Chachamim say, since it's a זה וזה גורם,
zeh v'zeh gorem since the last one could not have done it
all by itself, it needed the היתר, heter, so it was not
all affecting the חימוץ chimutz and therefore it is not a problem.
Okay, so the וחכמים Chachamim certainly hold זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem is okay, even when the איסור issur falls in at the
end. The question is what does רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer hold? By
the way, I should say two things. Number one is like I've
already said, this is not this is a case of תרומה, terumah
it's not a case of עבודה זרה. avoda zara Maybe we'd be
more strict by עבודה זרה. avoda zara. The other point is, the
problem here is not the question of did you derive benefit? The
problem here is the laws of ביטול. bitul. Does something not become
בטל batel, if it effected fermentation? So maybe the the way you
define whether it effected fermentation is different than the question of whether
it's considered like you derived benefit from an object. So you know,
the very anyway, it's interesting that the גמרא Gemara just thinks you
can compare the cases. Anyway, so the וחכמים Chachamim certainly hold זה
וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem. is not an issue. What about רבי
אליעזר? Rabbi Eliezer's What would רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer hold if they
both fell in at the same time? Would he hold that is
a problem or that's not a problem? So אביי Abaye is going
to help us understand this. ואמר אביי, v'amar Abaye, and אביי Abaye
says, לא שנו אלא שקדם וסילק את האיסור. lo shanu ela shekadam
v'silek es ha'issur. That when רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says that if
the היתר heter falls in in the end, you're good, okay, that's
only, see now Michael's even happier. He's trying to bring רבי אליעזר's
Rabbi Eliezer case closer to that of the וחכמים. Chachamim. Okay, that's
only if you had removed, you know, the the sourdough fell in
and it caused it started some fermentation process to go on and
then you removed it. And then the היתר heter fell. 'Cause then
you could really ignore the sourdough that the תרומה terumah that fell
in first 'cause it's already been removed. Okay, and that's where רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer's says it would be permissible if the היתר heter
fell in last.
שקדם וסילק את האיסור. shekadam v'silek es ha'issur. אבל לא קדם וסילק
את האיסור... aval lo kadam v'silek es ha'issur... assuming you can actually
identify... Yeah, yeah, yeah. Okay, if you did not, however, do that,
אסור, assur, it's forbidden. Now why? Because אביי Abaye is saying is,
even if it fell in first the תרומה and then the other
one, if the תרומה was still there when the היתר heter fell
in, so this is Michael's point, you don't just ignore the past
history, you say right now I have תרומה and חולין of sourdough,
they're both operating jointly to cause it, they're both actually present right
now and operating jointly to cause it to ferment, and that's a
problem. So according to אביי, Abaye, אביי Abaye basically says that רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer would say זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is
אסור. assur. Got it? וחכמים Chachamim say זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem is מותר, mutar, even when the איסור issur falls in at
the end, since it's always in conjunction it's always okay. So the
וחכמים Chachamim say when both of them are doing their job it's
okay. And רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer, says that as soon as both
of them are present and doing the job, it's a problem. And
רבי אליעזר's Rabbi Eliezer whole leniency was only if you removed the
איסור issur before the היתר heter fell in. Okay, so אביי Abaye
is making רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer very big scope, it's a problem
when they're both doing it. So according to אביי, Abaye, that's the
debate, whether זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is אסור assur or
מותר. mutar. Okay, again the thing is why we assume this is
relevant to עבודה זרה avoda zara? is not as clear. But אביי
Abaye says here the way אביי Abaye explains this debate, we finally
have a clear debate of תנאים Tannaim whether זה וזה גורם... zeh
v'zeh gorem, זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is אסור assur or
מותר. muttar. So the חכמים, Chakhamim, it's clearly מותר, muttar, they're both
present and even the איסור issur fell in last and even so
the חכמים Chakhamim say it's fine because they're both operating together and
according to אביי, Abaye, if they're both present according to רבי אליעזר,
Rabbi Eliezer. it's אסור. assur. Okay, so that's a clear debate according
to אביי. Abaye. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי מאי דטעמא דרבי
אליעזר כאביי? u-mimay d'taama d'Rabbi Eliezer k'Abaye? The גמרא Gemara says, okay,
that's all very nice but since when are we locked into אביי's
Abaye read of that debate? According to אביי, Abaye, that's the debate
of זה וזה גורם. zeh v'zeh gorem But who says we agree
with אביי? Abaye? דילמא טעמא דרבי אליעזר משום דאחר אחרון אני בא?
de-ilma taama d'Rabbi Eliezer mishum de-achar acharon ani ba?
Maybe רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer holds זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
is מותר muttar like the חכמים Chakhamim and if they both fell
in at the same time, it would be fine. The only problem
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer has is if the איסור issur falls in
at the end, then I only focus on the איסור, issur, I
don't look at them... what? Yeah, I don't look at them operating
together. I say what happened in the past happened in the past
and the last one is the one that did it. If they
come together, then I'll say it's מותר. muttar. Okay, איגמר באיסורא אסורה
ואיגמר בהתירא מותרין בין סליקה בין לא סליקה, igmar b'issura assura v'igmar
b'hetera muttarin bein selika bein lo selika,
whether you removed the היתר, heter, whether you removed the first thing
or didn't remove the first thing. זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
is fine according to me, he says, if they fell at the
same time. But if they fell sequentially, I'll focus on the last
thing, which is the easy way to read רבי אליעזר. Rabbi Eliezer
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, look, according to אביי, Abaye, maybe
that's the debate and anyway that's just a debate about תרומה and
so on and ביטול, bitul, but anyway we don't have a clear
debate of רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and the רבנן rabbanan, about זה
וזה גורם. zeh v'zeh gorem אלא רבי אליעזר ורבנן דעצים. Ella Rabbi
Eliezer v'Rabbanan d'eitzim. Fine, how about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and רבנן
rabbanan about the wood? And now finally here we're honing in on
something that actually fits better because it's going to be about עבודה
זרה avoda zara and actually it's the next משנה Mishnah that's coming
up when we turn the page. Okay, here's the next משנה Mishnah
coming up,
דתנן: נטל הימנה עצים, Natul mimena eitzim, you took this אשרה Asherah
tree and you broke off some wood to use for fire, that's
forbidden, right? You're getting הנאה hana'ah from the אשרה Asherah tree. אסורה
בהנאה. Assura behana'ah. You can't get benefit from this wood you broke
off from the tree. הסיק בה את התנור. Hisik bah es hatannur.
Now you went ahead and you ignored us and you went ahead
and you took this firewood and not only did you make like
a little barbeque over it which would have been forbidden, you actually
used it to fire up an oven. Now the problem with firing
up an oven, I mean if you're just going to cook in
the oven it's like making a barbeque, whatever, like having a campfire.
But if the oven is a new oven, you're doing something else
with it. You're strengthening the oven, you're like final... you're like, you
know, after they would make an oven it's like putting it in
a kiln, it gives it its hard... it hardens it. And now
it's going to be an enduring problem because after you've done this,
every time you're now going to use the oven after this first
time, you are getting benefit from the fact that that wood initially
caused the oven to be strong and now the reason the oven
is cooking is all thanks to that initial firing up that you
did with the אשרה Asherah wood. Now when you do that though,
imagine now it's a week later, I fired it up with the
אשרה Asherah wood a week ago, now I'm cooking my bread in
this oven. So what's causing this bread to cook? It's partly being
caused by the current fire and it's partly being caused by the,
you know, the strengthening of the oven, the presence of the oven
that has, you know,
so therefore the bread is being cooked by a contribution of the
current fire and the old firewood that, you know, a few stages
removed but indirectly is helping this bread cook. And actually, apparently when
you have a brick oven for cooking bread, the bread is actually
not cooked by the fire. I mean, well it is but indirectly.
The way it works is that the fire, the heat of the
fire gets absorbed into the bricks and then the bread is cooked
by the heat that is then released by the bricks that they
absorbed by the fire. So anyway, if you appreciate that, I think
it even helps understand again that sort of the bread is being
cooked by the oven, not just by the fire, and that oven
was strengthened and created by that initial burning. So that's like a
זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem type of a case. Okay? And
that's an עבודה זרה avodah zarah type of a case. Okay? אלא
רבי אליעזר ורבנן דעצים. Ella Rabbi Eliezer v'Rabbanan d'eitzim. דתנן: נטל הימנה
עצים, Natul mimena eitzim, אסורה בהנאה. assura behana'ah. הסיק בה את התנור.
Hisik bah es hatannur. You used this wood to fire up an
oven. חדש יותץ ישן יוצן. Chadash yutat yashan yutzan. So if it's
a new oven you have to break it because you can't continue
to use this oven because it'll be a זה וזה גורם zeh
v'zeh gorem problem. If it's an old oven then it didn't really
strengthen the oven so just let it cool off and then there'll
be no more הנאה hana'ah, from the wood. But an old oven...
if it's an old oven, excuse me, but if it's a new
oven then you've now created an oven with this wood and you
have to break the oven. אפה בו את הפת אסורה בהנאה. Afa
bo es hapas assura behana'ah. Now let's say you went ahead and
you did cook bread in this oven. So there are two scenarios,
right? In either scenario it's a זה וזה גורם, zeh v'zeh gorem
right? The scenario of the old oven, here's the old oven and
here's your אשרה Asherah wood. Okay, okay, and in that case and
here's your bread, okay, so it's a זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem because you have the היתר heter benefit created by the old
oven and the איסור issur benefit created by the current אשרה Asherah
wood. Okay, that's if it's
if it's old. If it's a new oven and now this is
non-אשרה Asherah wood, this is היתר heter wood, okay, this is a
case of a new oven, okay. Well it was new a week
ago. Okay, when it was new these walls here were strengthened, they
got the... You understand a week ago when you cooked it. Okay,
so in this case, it's a זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
in the opposite.
But you had to break it already, didn't you?
What? You didn't. Okay, so you were supposed to cool it off
or you were supposed to break it, but you didn't. So in
either scenario, it's a זה וזה גורם. zeh v'zeh gorem Either the
אשרה Asherah wood creates the direct heat and the oven creates the
sort of is it by storing the heat and releasing the heat
and so on, and this is היתר heter and this is איסור,
issur, or you created it a week ago and it was a
new oven. So now the היתר heter wood is creating good heat,
but the fact that the oven was created with the אשרה Asherah
makes this a way of getting benefit from the אשרה Asherah and
so in either way, you know, the wood, the אשרה Asherah wood
is giving you one of the benefits. Okay, so what do you
do now?
Okay, אפה בו את הפת, afah bo et hapat, אסורה בהנאה, asurah
behana'ah, you can't benefit from the bread. Okay, that's a זה וזה
גורם zeh v'zeh gorem. is אסור assur by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah.
That's essentially what it's saying. Now, נתערבה באחרים, nitarvah ba'acherim, now let's
say this loaf of bread got mixed up with other loaves of
bread, so כולן אסורות בהנאה. kulan asurot behana'ah. Since it's a loaf
of bread, you can't derive benefit by עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. Yeah,
but even by עבודה זרה avodah zarah. we wouldn't go further. Okay,
but yes, that could be an interesting fact or two. But anyway,
the short answer is by עבודה זרה avodah zarah we don't do
ביטול. bittul. Okay? So this loaf of bread got mixed in other
loaves of bread, you can't eat any of them. Now, רבי אליעזר
אומר, יוליך הנאה לים המלח. Rabbi Eliezer omer yoliach hana'ah l'yam hamelach,
רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says,
no, I got a way that you can eat the loaves of
bread. This loaf of bread was worth a dollar. It got mixed
up with a hundred loaves of bread. So I'll tell you what,
the problem is getting הנאה, hana'ah so take a dollar, flush it
down the toilet, and we'll say that you now are not benefit
now you are not benefit.
It can't be like חזר chozer though, or what?
I understand. So the point is is that since in principle this
thing really is בטל batel, and we're just being strict and not
allowing ביטול bittul to work, he's basically saying as long as you're
not going to net any benefit, right? If it really wasn't בטל,
battel then when you get around to it and you're eating it,
you're getting הנאה hana'ah from עבודה זרה. avodah zarah. But since the
real point is that really it is בטל, battel we're just not
allowing ביטול bittul to work, take the amount you would have benefited
from it, take a dollar, flush it down the toilet and now
we'll say you're not getting benefit.
But we say it was all החרם hacherem and it has to
be like literally the stuff, because the bread isn't the חרם, cherem,
it's just the אשרה Asherah stuff, right? Because before we had like...
Yeah, I mean even that is not clear that it's not ביטול.
bittul. That's probably the ביטול bittul issue is probably a דרבנן d'rabbanan
issue. אמרו לו, amru lo, anyway they said to him, אין פדיון
לעבודה זרה. ein pidyon l'avoda zara. Now, what are you talking about?
It's not like הקדש, hekdesh, you're going to transfer the status to
the dollar? You know, or it's not like a question about like,
oh in the net well you agreed to flush a dollar down
the toilet. Like, I'm sorry, when you got around to that loaf
of bread, you were benefiting from that loaf of bread. Okay, now
what is they really debating? So, if so, meaning why does רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer allow you to do this trick? I mean we
understand more why the רבנן Rabbanan don't. Why does רבי אליעזר Rabbi
Eliezer allow you? So רבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי אליעזר מאן נינהו? rabbanan
d'pligi alei d'Rabbi Eliezer man ninhu? So who are these rabbis that
argue on רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer and they're strict? אילימא רבנן דעצים,
ilima rabbanan d'etzim, אחמורי אחמיר,
אלא רבנן דשאור. achmorei achmir, ela rabbanan d'se'or. So who are these
rabbis? If they are the rabbis of the of
of hold on, let me just check רש״י Rashi a minute here,
make sure I'm saying this right.
Right, so I'm sorry. So the גמרא Gemara is saying like this.
So you see that both רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. and the רבנן,
Rabbanan meaning okay, they have this debate about flushing the dollar down
the toilet, but they both basically hold that the bread is forbidden,
right? Everybody see that? They both basically hold the bread is forbidden.
The only debate is can you flush the dollar down the toilet
if the bread gets mixed up with other loaves of bread? So
basically everybody of this משנה mishna holds זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem. is forbidden. All right? Everybody with me? So this is not
the position that's lenient. These are all the positions that are strict,
that hold זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem is forbidden. All right,
so let's take a look. So that's what the גמרא Gemara wants
to say. Great, you've shown me a רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer? that's
strict by זה וזה גורם, zeh v'zeh gorem where have you shown
me a רבנן Rabbanan. that's lenient? Right. אלא, ela, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
רבנן דפליגי עליה דרבי אליעזר מאן נינהו? rabbanan d'pligi alei d'Rabbi Eliezer
man ninhu? Now where are we going to find the rabbis that
are lenient and say that the זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem
is okay? אילימא רבנן דעצים, ilima rabbanan d'etzim, if it's the same,
if it's the rabbis who are debating him in this משנה mishna
itself by the bread, אחמורי מחמירי, achmorei machmiri, they're strict, they also
say the loaf of bread is forbidden, they're even stricter than him,
they say you can't flush the dollar down the toilet. So everybody
in this משנה mishna holds that זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem,
is a problem. אלא רבנן דשאור, ela rabbanan d'se'or, it's the rabbis
by the case of the you know of the sourdough. One minute.
אימור דשמעת להו לרבנן דמקילי בשאור. eimur d'shamat lehu l'rabbanan d'mekili b'se'or.
This is the point that I made earlier. There at most it's
a case of you know the sourdough and תרומה and so on.
בעבודה זרה מי מקילי? ba'avoda zara mi mekili? Whoever says it by
עבודה זרה? avoda zara, So we've got a problem. What's the problem?
So far everybody seems to say that זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh
gorem? by עבודה זרה avoda zara, is a problem. Okay, we've got
this case here about the wood and the... the oven we've got
the case about רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer. *Rabbi Eliezer* with the stuff
from the tree he's got a problem about the stuff that falls
down from the tree okay we've got the rabbis about when you
grind up the עבודה זרה avoda zara *Avodah Zarah* and scatter it
around that they're afraid so that was what we said before that
everybody holds זה וזה גורם zeh v'zeh gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem* by
עבודה זרה avoda zara? *Avodah Zarah* is a problem okay but then
we're stuck because we had that ברייתא *Braita* that said about feeding
the cow the fet or you know or fertilizing the field no
but
we also had רבי יוסי Rabbi Yosi, *Rabbi Yosi* in the משנה
Mishnah *Mishnah* that says it's okay right
because he says the חכמים *Chachamim* but the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says
that's because it's offset it that's the way we were explaining it
no
no שוחק וזורה *shochek v'zoreh* yeah
so the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara* said that's because it's you're just getting
rid of it and it probably won't lead to anything the גמרא
Gemara *Gemara* explained that yesterday okay so there was ways to deal
with that by doing it איפכא *ipoch* maybe but the way we're
basically approaching it now everybody is saying רבי יוסי Reb Yossi, *Rabbi
Yosi* רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer* the רבנן Rabbanan *Rabanan* זה
וזה גורם Zeh Vezeh Gorem. *zeh v'zeh gorem* by עבודה זרה avoda
zara *Avodah Zarah* is a problem we do have a ברייתא *Braita*
back there that actually said by the case about the the the
dung and the fertilizer in the field that it's okay by עבודה
זרה *Avodah Zarah* but we don't know who to ascribe that to
but at least everything that we can see that we can you
know more clearly explain is that it's a problem so now we're
back to our issue which our issue is is that how do
you explain right if everybody says it's a problem so let's take
a look at the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* so the גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
says אלא לעולם הא רבי יוסי Reb Yossi ורבנן *ela l'olam ha
Rabbi Yosi v'Rabanan* so we're going to go back to what we
said before okay that yes that the issue about what do you
call it about about the discussion of of the field with the
dung and so on is a debate of רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*
and the רבנן *Rabanan* so it is so one minute so now
how does this work so רבי יוסי לדיבריהם דרבנן אמרה להו *Rabbi
Yosi l'divreicham d'Rabanan amrah lehu* he's saying to them לדידי זה וזה
גורם Zeh Vezeh Gorem. מותר mutar. *l'didi zeh v'zeh gorem mutar* so
now I mean it's getting very confusing but let's try to sort
of line up the different things that we've had okay we have
the case of the oven that's רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer *Rabbi Eliezer*
and רבנן *Rabanan* and everybody says that is אסור *asur* okay we
have the case of the field and the dung
that was a מחלוקת *machlokes*
and that was a מחלוקת *machlokes* okay you have מותר muter, *mutar*
and אסור *asur* so that seems to be זה וזה גורם Zeh
Vezeh Gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem* by עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* is debated
okay but we don't know who said which one okay then we
had our case about the אשרה Asheira *Asherah* and the and the
droppings okay and in that case רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* said אסור
*asur*
and
the חכמים *Chachamim* said מותר *mutar* right and we said you could
explain it that the shade offsets the benefit but it seems to
be they're debating זה וזה גורם Zeh Vezeh Gorem *zeh v'zeh gorem*
and finally you have the שוחק וזורה לרוח *shochek v'zoreh l'ruach* the
grinding up of the עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* right where רבי יוסי
*Rabbi Yosi* the same רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* here says מותר *mutar*
and the חכמים *Chachamim* say אסור *asur* right so that got everything
very confusing okay so and there you could also say that the
reason רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* says מותר *mutar* is because it's not
likely that it'll lead to a problem but fundamentally it is so
you have all of this sort of conflicting evidence so what are
you going to do with all of this so the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* is going to say the following here's the way we're going
to do it this shows that there is some debate going on
okay so we're going to assume actually that רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*
says זה וזה גורם *zeh v'zeh gorem* is מותר *mutar* okay that's
fine because this is רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* and זה וזה גורם
מותר *zeh v'zeh gorem mutar* explains this so the חכמים *Chachamim* say
אסור *asur* so that's going to work this works this works and
then everybody agrees this works רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi* says מותר *mutar*
the only thing now so that's very nice it all lines up
the only thing now we're left with is that they seem to
switch positions here in the case of the אשרה Asheira *Asherah* okay
why is he saying אסור *asur* why they say מותר *mutar* they
could say the principle about offsetting right that the shade the bad
part of the shade offsets the good part of the droppings but
why is he saying אסור *asur* if fundamentally he holds it's always
מותר *mutar* so that's the that's the only thing we have left
to explain and we have the we're going to say it by
saying that he really is just sort of arguing to them based
like critiquing them and saying לדיבריהם *l'divreicham* he himself really agrees that
it's מותר *mutar* okay so so אלא *ela* says the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* fine you're right like you wanted to say before לעולם הא
רבי יוסי ורבנן *l'olam ha Rabbi Yosi v'Rabanan* רבי יוסי *Rabbi Yosi*
says it's מותר *mutar* and the rabbis say it's forbidden רבי יוסי
לדיבריהם דרבנן קאמר להו *Rabbi Yosi l'divreicham d'Rabanan ka'amar lehu* he is
just saying to them according to your position you're being inconsistent לדידי
זה וזה גורם מותר *l'didi zeh v'zeh gorem mutar* as far as
I'm concerned זה וזה גורם *zeh v'zeh gorem* is מותר *mutar* even
by עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* and that's why I say this is
מותר *mutar* and that's why I say this is מותר *mutar* and
so on בדידכו *b'didchu* but according to you דאמרתו זה וזה גורם
אסור zeh v'zeh gorem assur, *d'amritu zeh v'zeh gorem asur* that you
normally say זה וזה גורם *zeh v'zeh gorem* is a problem at
least by עבודה זרה *Avodah Zarah* אודו לי מיהת אף ירקות בימות
הגשמים *odu li miah af yarakas bimot hageshamim* then you should have
a problem with the vegetables in the winter because at least they're
getting the benefit of the droppings of the tree so when he's
saying אסור *asur* he's not really saying I think it's אסור *asur*
I think it's מותר *mutar* but you guys should be saying אסור
*asur* okay ורבנן *v'Rabanan* and the rabbis would say back כדאמר רב
Rav מרי בריה דרב כהנא *k'd'amar Rav Mari breih d'Rav Kahana* like
רב מרי *Rav Mari* says in the name of רב כהנא *Rav
Kahana* they would say back yeah but that's true maybe it should
be אסור *asur* but it's being offset by the bad
And our משנה Mishnah. is he's just critiquing the rabbis based on
their own position. Now, see Michael left, but Michael always wants to
know what the הלכה halacha is, and the punchline of the גמרא
Gemara, is, even though there's so much evidence seemed to point to
זה וזה גורם אסור, particularly this next משנה Mishnah which we're about
to get to about the oven, nevertheless, אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל
הלכה כרבי יוסי, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabbi Yosi, we
rule like רבי יוסי, that זה וזה גורם even by עבודה זרה
is going to be מותר. Which logically should mean that in the
next case about the oven, even though you're not allowed to use
it, if you did use it, then you would be allowed to
eat the bread, because that would just be a זה וזה גורם
contributed equally by the fire and the oven. Okay, now we're going
to have an application of this. ההוא גינתא דאיזדבל בזבלא דעבודת כוכבים,
Hahu ginnasa d'izdabal b'zivla d'avodas kochavim, just like that case we had
before. There was a certain field that was fertilized with fertilizer of
עבודה זרה.
שלח רב אמי קמיה דרב יוסף, Shalach Rav Ammi kamei d'Rav Yosef,
רב אמי Rav Ammi sent רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, can I use
the field? Now it's not exactly clear what stage the question is.
Can I plant the field was the question? Is the question the
stuff's already grown, can I eat the stuff? Right, there's an interesting
question at what stage is it considered to be you're just dealing
with the byproduct of it and at what stage is it considered
to be that you're directly benefiting from it. But anyway, so that's
not clear. But he said what's the story? אמר ליה הכי אמר
רב יהודה אמר שמואל הלכה כרבי יוסי, Amar leih hachi amar Rav
Yehuda Amar Shmuel halacha k'Rabbi Yosi, we rule like רבי יוסי, זה
וזה גורם is permissible even by עבודה זרה. Like I said, it
raises questions at what stage are you allowed to do it, like
planting the field seems a little bit different than benefiting from the
stuff that's already growing there. But anyway, that's how we rule זה
וזה גורם is permissible even by עבודה זרה. Okay, we turn the
page and now we are already prepared for the next
משנה. Mishna נטל ממנה עצים, Natal mimena etzim, you took this wood
from this אשירה asherah tree, אסורין בהנאה, assurin b'hana'ah, you can't get
benefit. הסיק בהן את התנור, Heesik bahen es hatannur, now you used
it to fire up an oven, like we said. אם חדש יותץ
אם ישן יוצן. im chadash yutatz im yashan yutzan. If it's a
new one, you have to let it cool down, if it's a
new, excuse me, one more time. If it's a new one you
have to break it, because then it's left a permanent benefit in
the oven, if it's an old one just let it cool down
and then you won't get benefit from the fire. אפה בו את
הפת, afa bo es hapas, you now baked the bread, and now
and in one of these either of those two scenarios, you know,
either you're getting benefit both from the אשירה asherah and from the
היתר, hetter, so in that case, אסורה בהנאה, assura b'hana'ah, it's so
this משנה mishna. assumes זה וזה גורם is a problem by עבודה
זרה and don't get benefit from the bread.
נתערב באחרות, nisarav b'acherot, if this loaf got mixed up with other
loaves, כולן אסורות בהנאה, kullan assurot b'hana'ah, you can't get benefit from
any. רבי אליעזר אומר יוליך הנאה לים המלח, Rabbi Eliezer omer yolich
hana'ah l'yam hamelach, at least in that last case, meaning I'm not
going to let you eat if you know which loaf it is,
of course you got to throw out the loaf. But if you
don't know which loaf it is and in principle it should be
בטל battel. but we're strict and whatever, we say don't get benefit,
fine, take a dollar, flush it down the toilet. אמרו לו אין
פדיון לעבודת כוכבים, Amru lo ein pidyon l'avodas kochavim, sorry buddy, that
doesn't do anything. It's very nice that you decided to throw out
a dollar, but that doesn't mean that when you actually are eating
the bread, you're not getting benefit from the bread and if it's
not בטל batel. it's not בטל. batel, Okay. נטל ממנה כרכור, Natal
mimena karkur, now let's say what you did is rather than using
the wood to make a fire, you used a piece of the
wood to make a shuttle, you know not a shuttle like they
have the S-train or whatever the shuttle, you know, a shuttle I
think it's called a shuttle, is that what it's called?
When you
have a weaver's pick? Pick? A pick?
Oh, okay, okay, okay, I thought what is that thing that...
I think that is the shuttle.
That is the shuttle. But okay, but it's apparently, okay, okay, I
thought this was the shuttle, it's a pick. Anyway, you make some
wood instrument from it, okay? Okay, fine, you made some wood instrument
out of it. אסורין בהנאה, assurin b'hana'ah, you can't get benefit. ארג
בו את הבגד, arag bo es habeged, you used this wood instrument
to weave a garment, אסור בהנאה. assur b'hana'ah. Now
this garment, if you get benefit from this garment, it's indirectly getting
benefit from the which is by the way I should point out,
right, that and that's also like the case of the oven. There's
a חידוש chiddush here too, putting זה וזה גורם aside. The חידוש
chiddush here is you don't say I already got the benefit, I
already transgressed, I used it to heat up my oven, I should
have used other wood. I used it to make this garment, I
could have I should have used another instrument. So I transgressed, but
that's the end of the story, right? The fact that we say
no, even though I've already transgressed and used it, if you're going
to wear the garment, you're going to indirectly have gotten benefit from
my use of that piece of wood, or if you eat the
bread, you're indirectly getting use from my fire, that's already a חידוש
chiddush because that's very indirect, right? The thing no longer exists anymore.
Nevertheless, that's what we say. Don't use the garment, אסור בהנאה. assur
b'hana'ah. נתערב באחרים, nisarav b'acherim, if this garment got mixed up with
other garments, ואחרים באחרים, v'acherim b'acherim, and those garments got mixed up
with other garments, okay, so even two degrees removed. That's a whole
discussion in the ראשונים Rishonim whether you have that גירסא girsa or
not. כולן אסורין בהנאה. kullan assurim b'hana'ah. You understand that scenario by
the way? Right, that scenario's only look at how many how many
degrees removed it is. Here's the pick. I don't know, whatever, we'll
just call that the pick. Okay, that helped me make my garment
here.
like my little tunic. Okay, now somebody is going to wear the
garment that's considered like they're getting benefit from this. That's already a
חידוש chidush because you're not really, the guy wearing the garment isn't
directly getting benefit from that pick. Now this garment gets mixed up
in a pile of a million garments, okay? And we say that
it's not בטל. batel. Fine, that's one thing, that we don't allow
ביטול. bitul. Then one of these garments gets mixed up into another
pile, right? So the likelihood is that this was not the garment
itself. But no, we're going to say this pile is a problem
and this pile is a problem. That's אחר באחר. acher b'acher. Now
there's a debate in ראשונים Rishonim whether you read that way, maybe
there's other ways to read it, maybe it means the whole pile
got mixed up, not just one of those piles, but it's quite
a good degree removed from this little pick that was used from
the tree. That just shows you how strict we're being about עבודה
זרה. Okay,
אחר באחר כולן אסורין בהנאה, acher b'acher kulan asurin behana'ah, they're all
forbidden.
רבי אליעזר אומר Rabbi Eliezer omer, יוליך הנאה לים המלח, yolich hana'ah
l'yam hamelach. yeah, just flush the dollar down the toilet, just flush
the dollar down the toilet. אמרו לו אין פדיון לעבודת כוכבים, amru
lo ein pidyon l'avodat kochavim, no, you can't do that. Okay, וצריכא,
utzricha, says the גמרא, Gemara you need to tell me both cases.
דאי אשמעינן קמייתא, d'ei ashmeinan kammaita, if he had just told me
the case of the firewood, בהא קאמר רבי אליעזר, beha ka'amar Rabbi
Eliezer, that's why רבי אליעזר Reb Eliezer. is lenient and if the
stuff gets mixed up he says just flush the dollar down the
toilet, משום דבעידנא דקא גמרה פת קלי ליה איסורא, mishum d'b'idna d'ka
gamra pas kalli leh issura, when the bread is, you know, is
done, the איסור, issur, the firewood, has been destroyed. So it's much
more, the sense that you're benefiting still now with the bread is
much more indirect.
אבל כרכור, aval karkur, but the case of the pick, דאיתא לאיסורא
בעיניה, d'ita l'issura b'einei, that the pick still exists when the guy
is wearing the garment, so there's something more concrete to say, it's
like you're still benefiting from the pick because the pick is still
around. So even though you're not directly using the pick, it's still
connected back to it. אימא מודי להו לרבנן, eima modi lehu l'Rabbanan,
maybe he'd agree to the רבנן and not allow this idea of
flushing a dollar down the toilet. ואי
אשמעינן בכרכור, v'ei ashmeinan b'karkur, if you just had the case of
the pick, בהא קאמרי רבנן, beha ka'amri Rabbanan, that's why the רבנן
would be strict and not allow flushing the dollar, אבל פת אימא
מודי ליה לרבי אליעזר, aval pas eima modi leh l'Rabbi Eliezer, but
the bread where the thing doesn't exist anymore when you're eating the
bread, maybe they would agree that there we could be more lenient.
צריכא, tzricha, you need to tell me both cases. Okay. אמר רבי
חייא בריה דרבה בר נחמני אמר רב חסדא אמר זעירי הלכה כרבי
אליעזר. Amar Rabbi Chiya breih d'Rabbah bar Nachmani amar Rav Chisda amar
Zeiri halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer. We rule like רבי אליעזר. Reb Eliezer. Now
again, that's pretty interesting, since a minute ago it sounded like זה
וזה גורם was, you know, we were lenient. Why do you even
need to rule like רבי אליעזר? Reb Eliezer Maybe the bread should
be totally okay, right? Because זה וזה גורם was okay. But at
least in this case, maybe it's not a זה וזה גורם. In
the case of the bread, you had both the fire and the
oven. Here you just have the pick as the one thing that's
being used to weave it or to do that part of the
weaving. So maybe this case at least is less of a זה
וזה גורם. Anyway, he says that if you have a case like
this, we would rule like רבי אליעזר. Reb Eliezer If it gets
mixed up or whatever, just take the dollar and flush the dollar
down the toilet. הלכה
כרבי אליעזר. halacha k'Rabbi Eliezer.
I assume that the גמרא's Gemara use of this משנה mishna, in
the previous discussion was only for discussion purposes and therefore the reading
of the part about זה וזה גורם is no longer applicable?
No, I don't know. Meaning it's true, maybe this גמרא Gemara seems
of course oblivious to what we just said on the עמוד א׳.
amud aleph. So you could say maybe it has a different read
of this and maybe it assumes that this is worse than a
זה וזה גורם problem. This certainly I think is not זה וזה
גורם because, right, it's just the pick, it's not like the fire
and the oven. So it's not clear whether this גמרא, Gemara like
based on what we learned on the עמוד א׳, amud aleph, at
least the case of the oven, the bread should be okay, right?
The גמרא never really tries to fit that together. And now so
to rule like רבי אליעזר means you're ruling that there is some
problem here. So there's one of two paths: either you could say
that actually the bread is worse than זה וזה גורם, or you
could say that we're talking about the garment and not about the
bread. Yes.
Why isn't the garment also זה וזה גורם? You've got the whole
rest of the loom and the stuff that she needs.
Right. So that gets to תוספות's Tosafot question that תוספות Tosafot claims
that זה וזה גורם is only when they're contributing to doing the
same thing. You know, now again I don't know, if the pick
is just part of, you know, getting, I don't know,
the stuff woven and that's also being achieved by the loom, you're
right. Like how different really is that than the fire and the
oven? Right? You know, they're contributing heat in different ways, but ultimately
it's about contributing heat. I'm trying to make sense of why the
גמרא thinks it's a problem, so I'm speculating that maybe the pick
does something that the other things don't do. But I don't know.
You're right, it's a good question. I mean, I haven't looked, I
need to look at the ראשונים Rishonim to see how they try
to make sense of this given what we learned on the עמוד
א׳. amud aleph. If you give me a minute here, let's see
quickly if the ר"ן Ran addresses it because, just one second, you
know, because it really does not seem to have incorporated what we
learned on the עמוד א׳. amud aleph. Very strange. So let me
see quickly if I can find you at least a quick answer
to this question.
Oh my god.
Since we rule like רבי יוסי,
we don't hold like this. The ר"ן Ran says since we rule
like רבי יוסי on the עמוד א', amud aleph, we don't hold
like this משנה. mishna
Therefore the whole bread is permissible.
And that's what the רי"ף Rif wrote. One minute. Okay,
so
the ר"ן Ran basically says like we suspected, that we don't rule
like this משנה, mishna, but he says, but he says at least
maybe to explain this case to the גמרא, that the case of
when if the firewood is itself the אשרה Asheira wood, even if
the oven is a היתר, heter, right in this case, he says
that would be stricter because since the heat is going straight into
the bread, that we would consider to be less of a זה
וזה גורם. Right, if this is the אשרה Asheira wood and this
is the היתר, heter, and the heat of the wood is going
straight into the bread, that he says is less of a זה
וזה גורם. So the case of the משנה mishna, could possibly be
where the case that we would still rule the bread is a
problem would be this case. Right, if the oven was the אשרה
problem, that wouldn't be an issue, but if the wood was, he
says that at least that might still be an issue. But yes,
bottom line is it's very strange. This גמרא is ruling like רבי
אליעזר and based on the עמוד א', amud aleph, it's זה וזה
גורם and the whole thing should be permissible, which is basically what
the ראשונים Rishonim say. Okay, but there are some cases that would
be considered not זה וזה גורם and still a problem. הלכה כרבי
אליעזר, Halacha KeReb Eliezer, we rule like רבי אליעזר. איכא דאמרי Ika
DeAmri others say, אמר רב חסדא אמר לי אבא בר רב חסדא,
Amar Rav Chisda amar li Abba bar Rav Chisda, said to me
my father, the son of רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, I guess the
elder רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, הכי אמר זעירי, Hachi amar Zeiri, this
is what זעירי Zeiri says, הלכה כרבי אליעזר, Halacha KeReb Eliezer, we
rule like רבי אליעזר. אמר רב אדא בר אהבה לא שנו אלא
פת. Amar Rav Ada bar Ahava lo shanu ella pat. Now this
is only true about bread. That because the bread is not the
thing of איסור issur itself. Remember, the bread just was baked with
forbidden אשרה wood. So since it's not the איסור issur itself and
it gets mixed up, we can say alright, you don't have the
איסור issur itself, you have indirect הנאה and it got mixed up,
just flush the dollar down the toilet. אבל חבית, Aval chavit, if
you have a barrel of יין נסך, yayin nesech, you have a
barrel of forbidden wine and that barrel gets mixed up with other
barrels and that barrel with other barrels or whatever the case might
be. There it's not like you're indirectly benefiting from some other thing
that was the problem. The wine itself is what is forbidden. Okay,
everybody hear that difference? It's not something produced by something forbidden, the
wine itself is forbidden. In that case you can't just take the
dollar and flush it down the toilet. לא, רב חסדא אמר, Rav
Chisda amar, no, אפילו חבית מותרת, afilu chavit muteres, even that case
is okay. Once it got mixed up, in principle it should be
בטל, batel, even if it's the forbidden object itself. We'll let you
just flush the value of the, if the barrel is worth $100,
just throw the $100, it seems like a big waste flushing $100
down the toilet, but then we'll say you didn't get benefit because
you threw out the $100.
Well I'm going to talk about drinking in a minute, that's an
excellent point, I'm going to get to that in a minute. ההוא
גברא דאיתערב ליה חביתא דיין נסך בחמרא. Hu gavra deistarvelei chavita deyayin
nesech bechamrei.
So a certain man got some יין נסך yayin nesech mixed up
with his wine. אתא לקמיה דרב חסדא, Ata lekamei deRav Chisda, he
said to רב חסדא, Rav Chisda, אמר ליה שקול ארבע זוזי ושדי
בנהרא ולישתרי לך. Amar lei shkol arba zuzei veshadei benahara venishtrei lach.
Take four זוז, zuz, throw it in the river and we'll permit
it to you. Now part of the other חידוש chiddush about רב
חסדא Rav Chisda is, my guess would be that a barrel of
יין נסך yayin nesech would be worth a lot more than four
זוז. zuz. So there's another חידוש chiddush here. Not just that we're
saying it by even the איסור issur itself, but we're even allowing
a more pro-forma throwing out of money, it doesn't have to be
really the full value. Now I want to pick up on something
that David said and רש"י Rashi clarifies two points.
One point רש"י Rashi clarifies is the following, is that this case
is that I want to benefit from I don't know these barrels
of wine. We'll get to drinking in a minute. But let's say
I'm not going to drink these barrels of wine, I have non-Jewish
workers and I want to feed it to them. So I'm going
to benefit from them, I'm going to use it to feed my
workers and so on. So that's the scenario that we're talking about
etc. He says, but let's say, and that's where there's a debate,
can I just take the money and flush it down the toilet?
But let's say I'm not using the wine directly. I'm going to
take these hundred barrels of wine and now there are 101 because
one barrel of יין נסך yayin nesech got mixed up, and I'm
going to sell them to my non-Jewish friend here Christopher, okay? Now
normally they would go for a dollar a barrel, so normally the
price would be $101. I'm going to sell it to him for
$100. You got the case? Okay, so רש"י Rashi says in this
case everybody would agree it's okay. This isn't a debate of רבי
אליעזר and the רבנן. The debate of רבי אליעזר and the רבנן
is where I'm benefiting from every single barrel, but because I flushed
a dollar down the toilet you're going to tell me
it's... But in the case where I take the whole hundred and
one barrels and sell them for a hundred dollars, I didn't receive
any benefit from that barrel because I didn't charge him for that
barrel. I only charged him for the hundred היתר heter barrels. What
I basically said to him is I'm charging you for the hundred
היתר heter barrels, one of these barrels is איסור issur that I'm
throwing in for free. So if I gave it to him for
free, I didn't get any benefit out of it. You hear that
case? So when I sell the whole lot and don't charge for
that extra איסור issur that's mixed up in it, everybody agrees it's
okay. The question is what I want to directly use it, does
flushing the amount down the toilet make it okay? Because that's hard
to understand why that work? At the end of the day, I'm
using it. But now we have question number two, which is David's
question. David says, so if I do this and I flush the
amount down the toilet, can I eat all the loaves of bread?
Can I go ahead and and and drink the wine? So רש"י
Rashi says no. רש"י Rashi says that would actually be eating it.
What by throwing the amount down the toilet, we're saying like you
didn't get benefit. Right, the prohibition of benefit
is a, is, you know, an extension, like it's beyond the prohibition
of eating. So if just because you flushed money down the toilet
doesn't mean you can eat something that's not allowed to be eaten
from. So when we're dealing with it on the eating plane, no,
you're still not allowed to eat it. But when we're dealing with
it on the benefit plane, we could say, oh, if you've already
thrown the amount down the toilet, we're going to view it like
you didn't really benefit from it because net, your bank account hasn't
improved as a result. So throwing out that money solves the benefit
problem because your bank account did not improve thanks to this, but
it does not solve the eating problem. So רש"י Rashi makes that
point very clearly in his פירוש perush that you mentioned that. Okay,
let's look at this next משנה, let's finish up the פרק. perek.
כיצד מבטלה, Keitzad mevatla, how would a non-Jew, because only a non-Jew
could be מבטל mevatel עבודה זרה, what would he have to do
to the tree in order to מבטלה mevatla it? כירסם וזירד, Kirsam
vezireid, let's say he basically took from it a, you know, a,
what do you call it,
a twig in order like kindling. He broke off some kindling,
okay, or נטל ממנו מקל, natal mimenu makel, or he took from
it something to use as a stick, meaning he broke off something
from the tree to use for his own purposes. So obviously you're
not treating it as עבודה זרה, you're using it for your own
purposes if a non-Jew does it. Okay, if a non-Jew worshipped it
and then a non-Jew can be מבטל mevatel it. או שרביט, O
sharvit, okay, which is and then like, you know, the, like by
פורים, Purim, right? The מקל makel is like a walking stick, a
שרביט sharvit is a scepter. Anyway, אפילו עלה עלה, afilu ala ala,
even if he just took a leaf, okay, because my kid has
a little fall project and they have to collect leaves or something.
הרי זה בטלה. Harei ze batla. That is an act of ביטול,
bittul, you're taking from the tree for your own purpose, you the
non-Jew, you're showing you don't treat it as a god.
שיפה לצרכה, Shifa letzorkah, now let's say he basically type of, you
know, like shaved it. If it is for the sake of the
tree to make the tree look nicer, to help the tree grow,
אסורה, asura, it's forbidden, because that's not ביטול. bittul. It's not just
the physical removal of something. You need two things: the physically break
something off and for your sake. If it's for the tree's sake,
it's not, it's still forbidden. שלא לצרכה, Shelo letzorkah, if it's not
for the tree's sake,
מותרת, muteres, then it's okay because then that's again, that's just taking
it for your own personal use. Okay, so now the גמרא says,
אותן שבאין מה תהא עליהן. otan shva'in mah tehei aleihen. Those shavings,
what's their story? Okay, so meaning if it's not בטל. batel If
it's בטל, batel. you did it for your own purpose, the tree
is permissible, obviously the shavings are permissible. But let's say you're doing
it for the tree's purpose. So the tree remains a problem, but
is the shavings still a problem? The things that were removed from
an עבודה זרה tree? Or is it at least that it's considered
a type of ביטול bittul on the shavings themselves? If the non-Jew
makes the shavings. Right, if you break something off, like in the
previous משנה, it's forbidden obviously. But the non-Jew breaks something off for
the sake of the tree, he's not מבטל mevatel the tree, but
is he implicitly at least meaning that the shavings are no longer
עבודה זרה? Okay,
so פליגי דרב הונא וחייא בר רב, pligi de-Rav Huna ve-Chiya bar
Rav,
a debate. חד אמר אסורים, chad amar assurim, the shavings remain forbidden,
וחד אמר מותרים, ve-chad amar mutarim, they're permissible. תני כמאן דאמר מותרים.
Tani k'man d'amar mutarim. We taught a ברייתא like the one said
permissible. דתניא, De-tanya, עובד כוכבים ששיפה עבודת כוכבים, oved kochavim she-shifa avodat
kochavim, a non-Jew is sort of shaving an idol. לצרכו, Letzorko, for
his own purpose, so that's a ביטול. bittul. The idol and the
shavings are permissible. לצרכה, Letzorkah, for the sake of the idol, he,
I'm sorry, his, okay, לצרכה, Letzorkah, for the sake of the idol,
היא אסורה, hi asura, the idol remains forbidden, ושבאה מותרים, ve-shva'eha mutarin,
but the shavings are permissible, because clearly the shavings, it's an implicit
ביטול bittul on the shavings, okay. ישראל ששיפה עבודת כוכבים, Yisrael she-shifa
avodat kochavim, but if a Jew does it, בין לצרכה בין לצרכו,
bein letzorkah bein letzorko, whether it's for the sake of the idol
or for his own sake, so היא ושבאה אסורים, hi ve-shva'eha assurim,
you a Jew can't do ביטול, bittul, okay, and therefore everything remains
forbidden. אתמר, Itmar, so that's the debate, whether it's a ביטול bittul
on the shavings. אתמר Itmar was taught. עבודת כוכבים שנשתברה, Avodat kochavim
she-nishtabra, let's say an idol... And this echoes earlier discussions at the
beginning of the פרק, perek, you might remember them, תוספות Tosafos tries
to align them with the earlier discussions, but we're just going to
focus on what we have here. An idol falls and breaks on
its own accord. Okay, it's like the Avrom story. What happened? Oh,
it did it to itself, you know? Anyway, is the fact that
it broke an implicit ביטול? bitul? Does it need a conscious act
of ביטול bitul by the non-Jew? Or the fact that it's in
a broken state would automatically mean that that's not a type of
thing they would worship anymore and that itself has changed its status?
Okay, so. עבודת כוכבים... avodas kokhavim... where were we? שנשתברה, shenishtabera, it
broke. רב אמר Rav amar צריך לבטל כל קיסם וקיסם. tzarich levatel
kol kisam v'kisam. A non-Jew would have to... would have to be
מבטל mevatel every single little piece, splinter. It's not בטל batel? and
every little splinter would need to be בטל. batel. ושמואל אמר v'Shmuel
amar עבודת כוכבים אין בטילה אלא דרך גדילתה. avodas kokhavim ein batila
ela derech gedilasa. You can only... now the way this reads, the
גמרא's going to amend it in a minute. You can only negate
its status, be מבטל mevatel it, if it's in its natural state.
Which sounds like what? It should be easier to be מבטל mevatel
in a broken state. So the גמרא says אדרבה, adaraba, what do
you mean? The opposite makes sense. דרך גדילתה מי מבטלה? derech gedilasa
mi mevatela? If it's growing normally, how does it become בטל? You
know, it's only when something's changed that we're talking about ביטול. bitul.
אלא הכי קאמר, ela hachi ka'amar, here's how to read it. אין
עבודת כוכבים צריכה לבטל, ein avodas kokhavim tzricha levatel, the only time
you have to do ביטול bitul is אלא דרך גדילתה, ela derech
gedilasa, if it's growing naturally. If it fell down and broke or
whatever, it doesn't even require ביטול. bitul. Okay, right, it's in a
state that nobody would worship it, it presumably doesn't even require conscious
ביטול. bitul. לימא בהא קמיפלגי, leima b'ha kamiflagi, let's say this is
the debate. דמר סבר עובדין לשברים demar savar ovdin lishvarim ומר סבר
אין עובדין לשברים. umar savar ein ovdin lishvarim. Maybe the debate is
do non-Jews, would they continue to worship the broken parts of an
idol? They didn't actively do ביטול. bitul. Their idol broke. Do they
still consider their idol to be holy and to be some embodiment
of their god and something still worthy of worship? Or do they
automatically say no, something it obviously... you know, how do they treat
it? Do they treat it as no longer something that holds this
power? Okay, so that's a reasonable way of framing the debate. לא,
not necessarily. דכולי עלמא עובדין לשברים, d'chulei alma ovdin lishvarim, I could
say everybody agrees they would still be prepared to worship the broken
pieces. Really? So then why is שמואל Shmuel lenient? והכא בשיברי שיברים
קמיפלגי. v'hacha b'shivrei shevarim kamiflagi. It's something that broke off of what
broke off. Meaning the fact that רב says קיסם, kisam, קיסם kisam
is like a splinter. Okay, we're not talking about big pieces. It
fell and it's in big pieces, that's one thing. But you have
a little bit of like dust and rubble and little chips, that's
the debate. Okay, so maybe that's where they're debating is the little...
the chips of the broken pieces. מר
סבר שיברי שיברים אסורים, mar savar shivrei shevarim asurim, they remain forbidden,
ומר סבר שיברי שיברים מותרים, umar savar shivrei shevarim mutarim, they're permissible.
Okay, and maybe they all agree though the big chunks are forbidden.
ואיבעית אימא, v'iba'is eima, if you want I could say דכולי עלמא
שיברי שיברים מותרים. d'chulei alma shivrei shevarim mutarim. Everybody agrees the little
chips are... are okay. והכא בעבודת כוכבים של חוליות. v'hacha b'avodas kokhavim
shel chuliyos.
We're talking about an idol that actually has parts that can be
assembled and disassembled. ובהדיוט שיכול להחזירה קמיפלגי. u'v'hedyot sheyachol lehachzira kamiflagi. And
it's a type of a case where it fell apart, but even
a non-expert could reassemble it. מר סבר כיון דהדיוט יכול להחזירה לא
בטילה. mar savar kivan d'hedyot yachol lehachzira lo batila. So if it...
you know, one would hold, look, even though it's in tiny little
pieces, what we would normally call שיברי שיברים shivrei shevarim and little
pieces would be מותר, but these little pieces, like Lego, it's a
tiny million little pieces, but in theory it could all be reassembled,
so it's not שיברי שיברים shivrei shevarim and it still is... and
it's still forbidden. ומר סבר אין עבודת כוכבים בטילה
אלא דרך גדילתה. umar savar ein avodas kokhavim batila ela derech gedilasa.
היינו אורחיה hainu orchei הא לאו גדילתה היא ואין צריך לבטל. ha
lav gedilasa hi v'ein tzarich levatel. An עבודה זרה's only בטילה batela
or only needs ביטול bitul if it's like in its natural state.
And now that it's in these tiny little pieces, even though in
theory it could be reassembled, it is not in its natural state,
and therefore it does not need ביטול, bitul, it automatically is considered
בטל. Okay, so that's a question at what state is an important
deeper question whether the act of ביטול bitul requires a conscious act
of the non-Jew to sort of... dis- you know, to make essentially...
to... you know, to sort of... the act is what changes its
status, or does just the reality that it's not in a state
that it would normally be worshipped enough to make the status go
away? And if you do say that reality is enough, then it
raises the question what circumstances satisfy that reality? What circumstances are those
that they would no longer worship it in this state? Okay. הדרן
עלך כל הצלמים. Hadran alach kol hatzelamim. And with that we will
finish.